Here we have a lab in EVE,
I'm showing this lab from
CCNP ENARSI. When you click on a
device, it will call the software that
I made to help with the programming
of this device.
It opens the software with a tab containing
the device's data. Looking down there
you can see telnet,
the IP, and the port.
So I double-click here on the tab and
I'll see the device data that
came from the call when clicking
on the device.
I can rename it, and this device is now
added to my software.
If I click on our red dot, it
turns green when connected, or stays
red when it's not connected.
Here in the script area I can write
the script,
I press ENTER, ENABLE and do a SHOW
running-config, I send my script,
notice down there that it sent an ENTER,
waited 500ms, typed EN for ENABLE, and after
500ms the SHOW RUN displayed the running
config. I click down here and use it as
if it were a normal terminal,
I can type, I can press tab here to
autocomplete, the question mark too if I
want, to see options, and I can
select and drag any text I
want. So I can work down there,
selecting text, dragging
it up and building the script. And I can
execute the script, it sends everything
down there with that delay between each
line.
Now running a new test, it did exit
there and went back to square one. If I
run the script again, it starts from zero,
it sends ENTER, ENABLE, sends
show running-config, and the show running-config
ended up sending the C of configure terminal, and went
into
it ended up going into running-config. Then
running again, here that
pesky name lookup issue showed up.
Then I can save, I save here, name it,
workspace 3 here, since I already had
the others. And I can load
workspace 2,
where I have two tabs, one with an SSH
connection to a Linux server and the other with
telnet to router 1.
It works the same way, SSH or telnet
with any device, whether local, on
the network, or in the emulator, so it works
well.
So here you can see, I'm
sending Bash code, it's
working. Look at the connection data:
IP, port, username, and password, because
SSH needs a username and password. If you
had a key you wouldn't need it, but in this case,
username and password.
And here I have the R1 script, so you see
that for each device it saves it there, and
on the side I can have the topology, an
image. I can zoom by scrolling the mouse, or
go left and right also by scrolling on the
mousepad left and right. I can
zoom in and select the area I want
to view better, drag it back and forth
holding the mouse button, or Shift while
scrolling the wheel, or even on the mousepad
scrolling two fingers sideways, I can
view the image.
And since I have EVE-NG, I don't need
this image. But if it were a real
topology, where I had the drawing,
I could have the drawing and the tabs with the
equipment here. I can view the
topology on the side and work on the
equipment over here.
So now with EVE here, I can leave
the topology in EVE and I can
connect to the equipment and start
working.
Here I have two buttons, Connect All,
which connects all devices, and
Send All, which sends a command to all
devices that are connected and
selected here in this tab.
So here I can select,
deselect what I want to send a
command to, and I send it to all.
So here if I add another
router, an R5 in this case, I'll rename
it to R5. Added, it's
disconnected. If I try to send, it
appears disconnected there and I can't
select it.
So I'll only send to those I
select.
So, I'll send to Linux, send
to R1, a clear command here.
So if I look at R5, it didn't
send anything, it's disconnected. On R1
it sent clear, which means nothing
to it, and on Linux here it did a
clear, went back to the original prompt,
so to speak.
I can come here and send another command
here, for example.
You see that for Linux it sends the
clear, clears the terminal, and I can send
this script that's up here.
I have to select here, I click here
on Select All, it selects all
the ones that are connected. The ones that
aren't connected can't be selected, it won't
send to them.
Now you see it sent the command
to the Linux terminal and to router 1
here as well.
So here you see I'm in a normal
terminal, I can type clear,
question mark, and it shows several
little commands.
And I can select the command I
want and simply drag and drop,
it places the command as if it had been
typed.
I can also drag, select,
drag and drop up there in the script
area, it goes right there.
I can also drag other things
from outside, a text I saw on the
internet, or a script that's in another
editor. I can grab that text that's
there, select it, drag, drop here, do
drag and drop, and I can work
with any other text too.
Now here if I go back and open my
workspace, it returns to the way it
was, with a saved script for
each device.
So, this part is working really
nicely, I can click there, it connects, then
that thing I mentioned, I can select
and drag here, drop, it pastes everything
there, I can edit here however I want,
and then send a command down below.
A text editor that highlights colors
for some commands, sometimes helps.
I can close the tab, save my
workspace, and also import from
EVE all the devices that are in EVE.
In this case I need to get the IP and the port.
The IP is there, oops, the IP is there, copy and paste.
The port is port 80, which is HTTP, I
don't need to change it. admin/eve, and here the LAB.
In this case the LAB is up there, I go
there, copy this LAB and paste it here in the right
place. Or if the name isn't there, I can
go to LAB DETAILS, the name will be
here too, I can copy it and paste it there.
When I press Fetch, it
connects to EVE and gets all the
devices that are in EVE. I set it
to sort starting with R, then SW,
and then the rest, in alphabetical
order.
Nice, the order looks good here. I can
select and deselect the ones I want to
import. On the side you see that EVE
disconnected, because it only accepts one
admin connection at a time, so later I
connect again.
And I imported all the devices here.
R1 already existed, it didn't overwrite it,
it kept the R1 that was there, and the ones that don't
exist, it creates.
I'll connect to EVE again, let's
go with the topology, and now when
I click on the device, it already selects
that device's tab here on the side,
because it already exists there.
So, if it doesn't exist, it would add a
new tab, since it already exists, it goes and
positions on that tab. It sees it's
telnet, the IP and port, sees there's a tab
with telnet, matching IP and port, goes
there and positions on that tab.
Here I can work with that
device, and each one will have its own
script. I can connect all, you see there
that it connected all, scrolling here.
I can now select the ones I want to
send a command to. I'll select all
here, they're all green. I'll send a
command here to all, so I send a
script here to all devices.
And let's do an enable, no cdp run,
to run a test. Ok, send. For Linux here the
enable caused some noise, the no cdp run
did nothing. But here on the first
router, it ran already,
configure terminal was missing, darn.
So enable, configure terminal, and
no cdp run, also with a 500ms delay,
will send to all.
I forgot to select all here,
darn!
Let's go, an ENTER, an ENABLE, a
CONFIGURE TERMINAL, and a no cdp run,
send to all devices.
Let's go, it sent to all the
selected ones, and you see there, there was an ENTER,
an ENABLE, CONFIGURE TERMINAL, no cdp run.
So if I switch between the other
devices, I'll see the same thing
happened, it sent that to all,
sent to the switch too, and if I go
scrolling, at the end there are PCs too.
It sent to the PC too, which are commands the
PC doesn't recognize. I shouldn't have selected
them when I set it to send, the
same thing, I shouldn't have selected
Linux there, it causes noise here.
But that's it, working nicely. I can
click on top and rename, since the
link between EVE and the tab is by the
IP and port protocol.
Now I can save this workspace
here, saved. I can type here, another
thing in this terminal.
I saved what I did here. If I open
another workspace, I'll load the things
from that workspace. If I open this
last workspace that I just saved,
it will restore exactly what I
had saved there, what I had typed.
So if I look here, each script
window will have its own script separate from
the others.
And I can add manually, so if
I have another computer or a
physical equipment, I can come here and
add this other equipment here. And
as I said, there's an image of the
topology that I can put on the side, when
it's a physical topology, and make this
kind of adjustment.
Well, that's it, the software is in a way
simple, but quite functional.
And as I keep clicking, it sends
the protocol, IP, and port, and it
positions on the correct tab for that
equipment.
And I can write here whatever script I
want only for that equipment, it doesn't
interfere with the others.
I can leave it here. And another thing here
is this Send Script button, it sends everything
that's here in the script editor. And there's the
Selected button, where the Selected button
sends only what's selected or the
line where the cursor is positioned.
So it was on that line
positioned on the ENABLE, it sent that
ENABLE, then it sent show IP ROUTE, missing
the "do", now it works perfectly.
So, I can send a selection inside
the script, or the whole script, or just
the line where the cursor is positioned,
and I can also copy something there,
select, and drag down, and switch
the device here, as I click in
EVE, it goes and switches the tab there.
And after opening the image, the next
step is to click on the image and select the
tab, map router 1, when
clicking on that area, it goes to the tabs and
selects the router 1 tab.
So that would be a next step, and
I'm also including AI in the project.
That's it.